Prelminary Guide to the Biological Sciences Department records, 1937-1979 RG0088
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Biological Sciences Department records
1937-1979
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Dept. of Biological Sciences
RG0088
1 Linear Feet 3 boxes
Materials in this collection include records of the various departments, including meeting minutes from the Department of Biology. They range in date from 1937-79.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 and 3 are closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials were transferred to the University Archives by the Chair of the Department of Biological Sciences.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Department of Biological Sciences of The George Washington University offers research and study on a broad range of biological topics, from the molecular level to the organismal and ecosystem levels and on organisms covering a broad spectrum of taxonomic diversity. The Biological Sciences major is one of the most popular in the Columbian College, especially among students preparing for medical, dental, and veterinary programs and graduate programs in biology, zoology, and botany. Faculty and graduate students are actively engaged in research here on campus and in field sites around the world, and often collaborate with researchers at one of the many research institutes in the Washington, D.C., area.
Degree work includes courses in genetics, molecular biology, physiology, ecology, and botany. In the 1930's-50's course of study in geology, zoology, and psychology were also part of Biological Sciences. Dr. Donnell B. Young was the chair of the department from 1933-53, and served as assistant dean of the Junior College in Columbian College from 1939-44 in charge of science and premedical curricula. Dr. Edith Mortensen, is another prominent person in the history of the department, serving as a professor of zoology from 1936-72.
From 1965-72 the department published the bi-monthly newsletter of the Commission on Undergraduate Education in the Biological Sciences (CUEBS). The program was organized in 1963 and administered by Washington University in St. Louis until 1965, when the grant was transferred to GW. CUEBS marked the start of a cooperative effort by member of the biological sciences community to deal with education in biology and curriculum revision and change.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include records of the various departments, including meeting minutes from the Department of Biology. They range in date from 1937-79, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Chair of the Department of Biological Sciences.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Departmental records 1937-1973; Departmental records 1977-1979; and Meeting minutes.
Biology; Botany; Science; Zoology; Biological Sciences; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Washington (D.C.); George Washington University; George Washington University. Dept. of Biological Sciences. Commission on Undergraduate Education in the Biological Sciences
- Departmental records, 1977-1979; RG0088 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains records from the consortium of biology from 1977 to 1979.
  Formerly ACC#39
  - Annual MiniSymposium of the Biology Departments of the Consortium of Universities and Colleges, 10/12/1979-10/13/1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Includes correspondence, schedule of events, abstract schedule, memo of sponsorship, and letters of invitation
  - Annual MiniSymposium of the Biology Departments of the Consortium of Universities and Colleges, 10/12/1979-10/13/1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mini-meeting on Biology in the District of Columbia, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Planning Memo
- Departmental records, 1937-1973; RG0088 Series 2; .25 Linear feet
  This series consists of correspondence, memos, newsletters, and office records from the Biological Sciences department. They range in date from 1937-73.
  Formerly vertical files
  - Biological Sciences - Commission on Undergraduate Education in the Biological Sciences (CUEBS), 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biological Sciences, Department of, 1968 ca.-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biological Sciences, Division of - Memos, Correspondence, 1937-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Meeting minutes, 1968-1978; RG0088 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series contains minutes from departmental meetings from 1968 to 1978.
  Formerly ACC#115
  - Minutes, Department of Biology, 1968-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)